Guide to the Patricia Miller Metro collection, 1950-2000 MS2359
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Patricia Miller Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority collection
1950-2000
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Miller, Patricia Ann
MS2359
5 Linear Feet
The Patricia Miller Washington Metropolitican Area Transit Authority collection largely consists of photographs and maps documenting the the construction of the Metrorail system between the years of 1950 and 2000. The collection also includes WMATA publications, including flyers and newsletters, that provide updates on the progress of the construction of the Metrorail system.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged into 3 series: Publications, Photographs, and Maps.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Patricia Miller, 8/26/2016 (Accession 2016.108)
Scope and Contents
This collection contains publications and maps of the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, photographs of the progression of the construction of the rail system, and oversized photographs mounted on foam core. The materials date from 1950-2000.
Historical
The Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, WMATA, with central offices in Washington, DC, is the private agency charged with the coordination and operation of mass transit in the National Capital Region. This area includes Montgomery and Prince George's Counties in Maryland, Arlington, the District of Columbia, and Fairfax County in Virginia.
The Interim Board of Directors of WMATA first met in mid-October, 1966, chaired by Brig. Gen. Jackson Graham, formerly Engineering Commissioner for the District. WMATA was formally established on February 20, 1967. WMATA formally received its charter in September 1967.
WMATA superseded the National Capital Transportation Agency (NCTA); a federal agency established by President Eisenhower in 1960 and inherited the bus and rail plans of the NCTA. For bus operations, WMATA bought out the routes from the private bus companies operating within its purview (with the exception of Montgomery County's "Ride-On" system) and established a single operation, Metrobus, to serve in their place.
For the creation of Metrorail, popularly known as "the Metro," routes, designs, and plans were finalized by the late 1960s. Work on the subway component began immediately upon the creation of WMATA. DeLeuw, Cather were retained as chief engineering consultants. The firm of Harry Weese and Associates were named chief architectural consultants. Weese was sent on a worldwide tour of subway systems, in order to draw inspiration and ideas for possible station architecture. The final design, agreed upon by a special committee that included the District of Columbia Board of Fine Arts and several artists and architects, was proposed in 1968.
First ground was broken for the subway above the future Judiciary Square station on December 9, 1969. The Metro ran its first day of revenue service, on the abbreviated Red Line beginning at Dupont Circle, in June 1976. Public response was enthusiastic. The system was a highlight of the Bicentennial celebrations one month later, during which it transported thousands of visitors.
Biographical
Patrcia Miller first joined Bechtel, the engineering consultant to Metro, as a Senior Draftsman in 1974. Her work involved the installation of the various appurtenances which made the system work. These consisted of millions of dollars worth of contracts to oversee the installation of graphics, kiosks, traction power, automatic train control, fare collection, and track work.
In late 1983, WMATA decided that they could handle the engineering themselves. Miller opted to leave Bechtel and obtain employment with WMATA in 1984 as an Assistant Office Engineer. She stayed on with WMATA until her retirement as an Office Engineer in May of 2004.
Separated Materials
Two published maps have been separated from this series and cataloged. The maps are titled Washington, D.C., Transportation Map (1988) and Washington D.C. and Metropolitan Area (1976). These maps have been cataloged as part of the Special Collections stacks.
These maps are located on-site.
Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority; Local transit -- Washington (D.C.); Transportation; Subways; Miller, Patricia Ann
- Publications, 1950-2003; 1970-1999; Series 1; .5 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  The materials of this series include multiple different publications produced by the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, including Capsule History of WMATA, Metro Ride Guide, Metro Memo Tabloid, Intercom, Inside Metro, Metropolitan Times, and Metro Weekly.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by the name of the publication and chronologically within each publication.
  - Capsule History of WMATA, 1952-2002; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Inside Metro, 1995-2002; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Intercom, 1994; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Metro Memo Tabloid, circa 1970-1980; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Metro Ride Guide, 1978; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Metro Weekly, 1999-2003; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Metropolitan Times, 1996-1997; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Official Program Arlington Orange Line Celebration, 1979; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - [Washington Post Magazine: Tunnel Visions], 1991; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - WMATA Builders Update, 2000-2003; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - WMATA Turning, 1999; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Photographs, 1970-1995; Series 2; 1 Linear Feet
  The materials in this series predominantly consist of photographs that document the construction of the Metrorail system. Materials include both color and black and white photographs in various sizes.
  Arranged in no particular order.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    This folder contains photographs of the construction of the following Metrorail stations:
    Prince George's Plaza, Shaw, Wheaton, Van Ness, Woodley Park, Cleveland Park, Pentagon City, Greenbelt, Dunn-Loring-Merrifield, and College Park.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Greenbelt, U Street, Federal Triangle, Wheaton, Cleveland Park, Pentagon City, Prince George's Plaza, New Carrollton, Federal Center, and Foggy Bottom.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Federal Triangle, Prince George's Plaza, U Street, Foggy Bottom, Twinbrook, West Hyattsville, Greenbelt, Dunn-Loring, West Falls Church, Vienna, Takoma Park, Shaw, Rockville, and Medical Center.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    College Park, Wheaton, Shaw, Anacostia, Foggy Bottom, Farragut West, Crystal City, Federal Triangle, Reagan Airport, and L'Enfant Plaza.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Federal Triangle, Pentagon City, West Hyattsville, College Park, Prince George's Plaza, Huntington, Potomac, L'Enfant Plaza, and Twinbrook.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Tenleytown, Friendship Heights, Federal Triangle, Stadium-Armory, Federal Center, Mt. Vernon, UDC, Wheaton, West Hyattsville, Prince George's Plaza, Greenbelt, Dunn-Loring, West Falls Church, and East Falls Church.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Reagan, Vienna, Dunn-Loring, West Hyattsville, Anacostia, Prince George's Plaza, College Park, Greenbelt, Shady Grove, Rockville, and Medical Center.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Shady Grove, Rockville, White Flint, Grosvenor, Prince George's Plaza, College Park, Metro Center, Wheaton, and Friendship Heights.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Cleveland Park, Van Ness/UDC, Rosslyn, L'Enfant Plaza, and Van Dorn.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Federal Triangle, New Carrollton, Potomac, Van Ness/UDC, and Foggy Bottom.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Foggy Bottom, Van Ness/UDC, Friendship Heights, Tenleytown, Pentagon City, L'Enfant Plaza, and Federal Center.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    L'Enfant Plaza, Pentagon City, Prince George's Plaza, Greenbelt, Foggy Bottom, U Street, and New Carrollton.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Prince George's Plaza, U Street, Friendship Heights, Tenleytown, Foggy Bottom, Pentagon City, Van Ness/UDC, West Hyattsville, and Navy Yard.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Navy Yard, New Carrollton, Prince George's Plaza, Foggy Bottom, Pentagon City, U Street, Anacostia, Cleveland Park, and Van Ness/UDC.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Federal Triangle, L'Enfant Plaza, Navy Yard, Van Dorn, West Hyattsville, Cleveland Park, Van Ness/UDC, Friendship Heights, Woodley Park-Zoo/Adams Morgan, West Falls Church, Fort Totten, Shaw, College Park, Pentagon City, and Tenleytown.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Shaw, U Street, Pentagon City, West Falls Church, Fort Totten, Anacostia, Foggy Bottom, College Park, and L'Enfant Plaza.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Greenbelt, Dunn Loring, Federal Center, Federal Triangle, Friendship Heights, Tenleytown, and Navy Yard.
  - [Photographs of construction], circa 1970-1995; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Navy Yard, Wheaton, Minnesota Avenue, L'Enfant Plaza, and West Hyattsville.
  - [Photographs of construction], 1996-2000, Series 2; 1 Linear Feet (Box 3)
- Maps, 1976-1988; Series 3; 1 Linear Feet
  This series contains maps of both the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit authority metro rail system, as well the Washington Metropolitan area in general.
  Separated Materials
  Two published maps have been separated from this series and cataloged. The maps are titled Washington, D.C., Transportation Map (1988) and Washington D.C. and Metropolitan Area (1976). These maps have been cataloged as part of the Special Collections stacks.
  These maps are located on-site.
  - [Proposed Plans for the Metrorail System] [cataloged title: Washington, D.C., Transportation Map (1988)], Series 3 (Map-folder 1)
  - Metro System Map [cataloged title Washington D.C. and Metropolitan Area], 1976; Series 3 (Map-folder 2)